Guide to the David M. Henderson Papers, 1964-1999 and undated RL.00529
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Subject File Series, 1964-1989 and undated, 6 boxes
  - Progressive Workers' Committee, 1973 (Box 6)
    Houses internal documents including Minutes, financial records, and inventory lists.
  - Progressive Workers' Committee, 1974 (Box 6)
    Consists of internal documents including minutes, financial records, and section committee reports. Also includes one General Bulletin.
  - Proletarian Cause, Black Liberation, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
    Houses three draft articles ranging from 4-28 pages.
  - Proletarian Cause, Communism, 1971-1972 (Box 6)
    Includes hand-written notes; three materials related to The White Blindspot; one essay entitled The Easy Road to Socialism: A Critique of the Communist Party Program; and two essay drafts related to worker conditions.
  - Proletarian Cause, Editorial Drafts, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
    Contains draft editorial statements, internal documents, article proposals, and one open letter.
  - Proletarian Cause, Labor, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
    Houses five pamphlets entitled Reform vs. Revolutionary Struggle in the Labor Movement, Mass Revolutionary Organization For the Workplace, The Anti-Marxist-Leninist Trend in the Progressive Labor Party, The Split in the Working Class and The Building of Fascist Labor Fronts, and 'Left' Opportunism-Twin Brother of Revisionism.
  - Proletarian Cause, Marxism-Leninism, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
    Consists of draft articles; one letter; and one 48-page essay titled The Crisis of U.S. Imperialism and the Prospects for Socialist Revolution in the '70s.
  - Proletarian Cause, Marxism-Leninism, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
    Contains draft articles including In the Working-Class Movement From 1900- World War I, Unity for the Revolution, The U.S. Revolution Will Triumph Without Jean-Francois Revel or the Ford Motor Company; and an untitled essay related to women and Marxism. Also includes one letter titled Build A Strong Marxist-Leninist Journal in Support of Open Debate Among Marxist-Leninists.
  - Proletarian Cause, Southern Editorial Board, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
    Contains internal documents and letters from Louisville Association of Communist Workers, Durham Collective, and Georgia Communist League (Marxist-Leninist).
  - Proletarian Cause, U.S. Imperialism and China, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
    Includes draft essays titled Working Class Unity and The National Question, The Needs of the U.S. Revolution, 1971-1972, Nixon's Visit, and an untitled essay related to the New Economic Policy.
  - Proletarian Cause, "Proletarian Cause", Sept. 1972 (Box 7)
    Houses one copy Proletarian Cause: Journal of Marxism-Leninism-Mao Tsetung Thought dated September 1972.
  - Gary F. Pugh, 1971 (Box 7)
    Houses 32-page school paper entitled The Soviet Worker In The Era Of Stalin (The Early Years: 1928-1937).
  - Radical Education Project, 1967, 1968 (Box 7)
    Includes two pamphlets including The U.A.W. Settles With Ford: Sellout and Insurgency in the Auto Industry and Labor and the South: Black Workers Set Against White-Strike Broken reprinted from Southern Patriot.
  - The Red Papers, 1972 (Box 7)
    Houses five issues of The Red Papers published by Bay Area Revolutionary Union.
  - Renaissance, Mar.-May 1969 (Box 7)
    Contains three issues of Renaissance: Newsletter of Duke Young Americans for Freedom including March 12, 1969; April 29, 1969; and May 8, 1969. The May 8, 1969 issue is a special issue that focuses on the R.O.T.C. student protest.
  - Revolutionary Union, 1972 (Box 7)
    Consists of oversized items including eight-page newspaper titled Victory Through Our Struggle, Not Through the Elections! Also includes one issue titled What Is Communism? published by Bay Area Revolutionary Union. The focus of the issue is on China.
  - R.O.T.C., 1969 (Box 7)
    Contains letter to Duke students and two drafts of letters written by Student Liberation Front; two posters and newspaper articles from The Duke Chronicle and The Durham Morning Herald ranging from April 15, 1969 to May 11, 1969; and Volume 1, Number 1 issue of The Duke No-No dated May 8, 197*.
  - Southern Student Organizing Committee (SSOC), 1963-1969 and undated (Box 7)
    Houses fourteen pamphlets reprinted from various sources and distributed by the SSOC. The titles include: The Power of the Dixiecrats by Tom Hayden; A Conversation-Jobs, Machines, and People by Ralph Helstein, Gerard Piel and Robert Theobald; Southern Mountain Tradition by Callie Cantrel and Luke Larmen; Folk Hereos and Protest by D.T.; Power and Racism by Stokeley Carmichael; Poverty and Affluence in Appalachia by Harry M. Caudill; West Virginia Wonderland by William C. Blizzard; The Southern Tenant Farmer's Union by H.L. Mitchell; Look Out Liberals: Wallace Power Gonna Get You! by Paul Valentine; The Southern Populist Movement, 1891-1896: A Political Analysis by Bruce Palmer; The KKK as an Exploited Class by Joe Neal; The South as an Underdeveloped Country by Robb Burlage; An Analysis of American Racism by Frank H. Joyce; and Mississippi's Economics and Mississippi's 'New Image'? by Mike Bruland. Also contains subscription letters; campus mailing schedule; Radical Southern History Conference agenda; bibliographies; contact lists; one tour schedule; one position paper; a report to the Student Liberation Front; and a work list.
  - Students For A Democratic Society (SDS), 1968-1970 (Box 7)
    Includes 31-page pamphlet entitled SDS Work-in 1968:Towards A Worker-Student Alliance. Contains a 4-page pamphlet entitled Reserve Liberal Training Corps (a play) and Suggestions for Building a Guerrilla Theatre Group produced by the Radical Arts Troupe of Berkeley SDS. Also consists of several types of membership cards; meeting flyers announcing the regional conference and actions; essays entitled The Fight For Women's Liberation, and Build A Movement to Smash ROTC, produced by the University; an essay that focuses on educational system; and communication from University of Utah Chapter. Contains flyers: Wanted for Exploitation, Racism and Murder! Columbia, the Boss! produced by Columbia University Chapter; and Free All Political Prisoners.
  - Students For A Democratic Society (SDS) Local, 1970 (Box 7A)
    Includes handwritten meeting notes.
  - Student Liberation Front, 1969 and undated (Box 7A)
    Contains financial records, Policy Conference notes, by-laws, handwritten letter and notes; and one Radical Newspaper broadside dated December 15 1969. Also includes Duke University account materials of Gary F. Pugh.
  - University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, 1969-1970 (Box 7A)
    Contains letters from J. Carlyle Sitterson, Chancellor; and C.O. Cathey, Dean of Student Affairs. Also includes Company Recruiting Visit List, Workers' strike (cafeteria workers) flyers, anti-racism flyers, anti-war flyer, and articles from The Durham Sun and The Durham Morning Herald.
  - Vietnam, 1969 (Box 7A)
    Contains flyers with topics including anti-war, military budget, anti-imperialism, and G.I.'s against the war. Contains conference paper titled Converting the Anti-War Movement written by the SDS Labor Committees. Contains eight-page newspaper titled Fire(Forces of Internationalist Revolutionary Energy).
  - Women's Liberation, undated (Box 7A)
    Houses essays titled The Political Economy Of Women's Liberation by Margaret Benston and The Fight For Women's Liberation. Also contains handwritten notes on female liberation and proposals for the organization.
  - Workers' Action Movement (WAM), 1973-1975 and undated (Box 7A)
    Consists of flyers with topics including anti-racism, movie viewing, Local 465, May Day, and support for New York City workers; two issues of Workers' Action!; and seven issues of WAM Newsletter with topics including Meat Cutters, Duke Workers and General Electric.
  - Writings, 1961 Jan.-1962 Jan. (Box 7A)
    Includes Henderson's handwritten school assignments for Beta English II Periods with Professor notes and grades.
  - Oversized Materials (Box 8)
    Houses two newspapers including a 12-page Trenton Rank and File, from July 1972; and the first issue of The Call produced by The October League. This 20-page issue includes articles in English and Spanish.